<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The antiquity of the Protestant religion with an answer to Mr. Sclater's reasons, and the collections made by the author of the pamphlet entitled Nubes Testium : in a letter to a person of quality : the first part.</title>
            <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53946</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1072</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1036</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11875609</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11875609</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50211</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53946)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50211)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 504:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The antiquity of the Protestant religion with an answer to Mr. Sclater's reasons, and the collections made by the author of the pamphlet entitled Nubes Testium : in a letter to a person of quality : the first part.</title>
                  <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 64, 56-59 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ben. Griffin, and are to be sold by Randal Taylor...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Pelling.  Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Errata on prelim. p. [2].</note>
                  <note>First edition.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sclater, Edward, 1623-1699? --  Consensus veterum.</term>
               <term>Gother, John, d. 1704. --  Nubes testium.</term>
               <term>Christianity --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Protestantism.</term>
               <term>Church history.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:50211:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:50211:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
THE ANTIQUITY OF THE Proteſtant Religion: WITH AN ANSWER TO Mr. <hi>Sclater</hi>'s REASONS, AND THE COLLECTIONS Made by the Author of the Pamphlet ENTITLED NUBES TESTIUM</p>
            <p>In a Letter to a Perſon of Quality.</p>
            <p>The Firſt Part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ben. Griffin,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Randal Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall.</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:50211:2"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen. Maurice R<hi rend="sup">mo</hi>. P. D. Wilhelmo Archiepiſcopo. Cant. à Sacris.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Dec.</hi> 13. 1686.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>for</hi> Aeneus <hi>read</hi> Aeneas, <hi>in the Margint</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>p.</hi> 22. <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>f.</hi> Canon <hi>r.</hi> Canons, <hi>p.</hi> 31. <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>f.</hi> where <hi>r.</hi> were, <hi>p.</hi> 41. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>f.</hi> moduling <hi>r.</hi> modelling, <hi>p.</hi> 59. <hi>l.</hi> 11. <hi>f.</hi> Contro-ſie <hi>r.</hi> Controverſie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:50211:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50211:3"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50211:3"/>
            <head>THE ANTIQUITY OF THE PROTESTANT RELIGION; With an Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Sclaters</hi> Reaſons, and the Collections made by the Author of the Pamphlet entitled <hi>Nubes Teſtium.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVHEN I receiv'd your Letter, I did at firſt a little wonder, that ſuch a knowing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhould deſire me to give a plain and particular proof of that Point which we Proteſtants do ſtand upon, that our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion was <hi>Anciently</hi> and <hi>Generally</hi> profeſt in the Chriſtian World, <hi>before</hi> the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. For the matter ſeems ſo clear to thoſe who converſe with Books, and will not ſuffer themſelves to be govern'd by partiality of judgment, that we may well be amazed at the great confidence of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50211:4"/>
Divines in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> who would fain perſwade you to believe the contrary; whether out of a deſign, or by means of their violent Paſſions and prejudices, I will not ſay.</p>
            <p>It is indeed taken for granted by peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple on that ſide, that at the Reformation their Church was the <hi>only</hi> Catholick Church in the World; and that their Faith was undoubtedly True and Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in all its particulars; becauſe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Church (as they conceive) muſt have <hi>failed;</hi> and the Promiſes of God, touching his preſerving and aſſiſting his Church to the Worlds end, muſt have come to <hi>nothing.</hi> Upon which falſe ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions they run away at all rates with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtrange notions of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> and of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi> believing and giving it out, that we forſook the True Church which was entitled to Gods Patronage and Guardianſhip, and did ſet up a new Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which no good Chriſtians ever own'd; and therefore that we muſt needs be in a miſerable and loſt condition.</p>
            <p>Seeing then the difference between us is ſo wide, either <hi>They</hi> or <hi>We</hi> muſt neceſſarily
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50211:4"/>
be under a very great miſtake: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in compliance with your commands I ſhall indeavour to ſatisfie you, that the miſtake lies not on our ſide; eſpecially, ſince the Author of the <hi>Nubes Teſtium,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sclater</hi> in his <hi>Conſenſus veterum,</hi> have taken ſo much pains to poſſeſs the World with a Notion to the contrary.</p>
            <p>In the proſecution of this matter I ſhall,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, take as ſhort and as particular a view as I can, of the State of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, from the Primitive times to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; and ſhew you how the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, we profeſs, were generally profeſt and own'd from Age to Age, in thoſe Churches which are nearer home.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That at the Reformation and before, the Faith of thoſe Churches, which are more Remote and diſtant from Us, was the ſame with Ours, in moſt of thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial points which lie now under debate. And when theſe Two things are cleared, ſeveral inferences will eaſily follow, which will abundantly ſerve to juſtifie Our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and to diſcharge the Proteſtant Religion from thoſe Imputations, which are commonly but unjuſtly caſt upon it.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:50211:5"/>
1. Firſt, let us look into the condition of Religion from the Primitive Ages to the time of the Reformation; and ſee, if thoſe Doctrines, which we Proteſtants profeſs, were not profeſt and own'd from Age to Age, before ever the Name of Proteſtant became a characteriſtical note of Diſtinction. And for the clearing of this, I think it too tedious to gather up <hi>Sentences,</hi> and ends of <hi>Sayings</hi> out of the Ancients, as Mr. <hi>Sclater,</hi> and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Nubes Teſtium</hi> have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to do. For they know well, that we have a <hi>Catalogus Teſtium,</hi> to which their <hi>Nubes</hi> is but as it were of a <hi>Hands breadth.</hi> And beſides the <hi>latter</hi> of theſe doth ingenuouſly confeſs, <hi>That many things in the Ancient Fathers are Obſcure; that their</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Preface</hi> pag. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Names have been prefixt to Books, of which they were never the Authors; and that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions have been made to ſome of their writings; beſides the divers miſtakes of Tranſcribers in the publiſhing of their Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The moſt effectual way therefore will be to obſerve the Doctrines of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents in their <hi>Diſputations</hi> and <hi>Controverſies</hi> with the Adverſaries of the Truth, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50211:5"/>
that, either when they purpoſely wrote againſt ſome known Error, and generally uſed the ſame arguments, as ſo many <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived</hi> Principles; or when they met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in <hi>Councils</hi> to ſettle matters by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Canons</hi> and <hi>Definitions.</hi> Theſe obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations will more readily, and more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly help us to underſtand the ſenſe of the Ancient Church, than our having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to this or that paſſage in particular Authors. So that if it be made appear, that our Religion is agreeable to that which the Ancients did in their <hi>Diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and <hi>Aſſemblies</hi> maintain, as the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Faith, you need not enquire further for your ſatisfaction, nor trouble your ſelf with Heaps of quotations out of <hi>ſingle</hi> Authors; unleſs you have a mind to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie your <hi>Curioſity,</hi> and for that you may conſult Biſhop <hi>Taylors Diſſwaſive,</hi> or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Mortons Appeal,</hi> or Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſhers An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Jeſuites challenge;</hi> which the Writers in this Age would do well to try if they can Anſwer.</p>
            <p>But to go to our buſineſs: It is noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, that the firſt great Controverſies in the Church were about the <hi>Common</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50211:6"/>
of Chriſtianity; a great many He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks for divers Ages, from <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> downward to Pope <hi>Honorius,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Monothelites,</hi> violently oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ſome the Reality of Chriſts <hi>Humane</hi> Nature; ſome his <hi>Divinity,</hi> ſome, the <hi>Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> between his two Natures; ſome, the Divinity of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> as a diſtinct <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> from the Father and the Son, and the like general Principles which the Chriſtian Church held. Againſt theſe Seducers, not only Books were written by the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Fathers ſeverally, but divers <hi>Councils</hi> were called; the firſt a <hi>Local</hi> Synod at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch</hi> againſt <hi>Paulus Samoſatenus,</hi> who taught that our Saviour was a meer <hi>Man.</hi> After this, Six general Councils met: The Firſt at <hi>Nice</hi> againſt <hi>Arius,</hi> for aſſerting that Chriſt Jeſus was a <hi>Creature:</hi> The Second at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> againſt the <hi>Eunomians</hi> and <hi>Sabellians,</hi> and the reſt that affirm'd the Holy Ghoſt to be a Creature too: the Third at <hi>Epheſus</hi> againſt <hi>Neſtorius</hi> for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving the Arian Hereſie<hi>:</hi> The Fourth at <hi>Chalcedon</hi> againſt <hi>Eutyches,</hi> who <hi>own'd</hi> the Divine and Humane Nature too, yet taught that upon the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of them, both were
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50211:6"/>
               <hi>mixt, Abſorpt</hi> and <hi>Tranſubſtantiated</hi> into <hi>One:</hi> The Fifth at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> again, to ſtifle a freſh the <hi>Neſtorian</hi> Blaſphemy<hi>:</hi> and the Sixth there <hi>alſo</hi> againſt Pope <hi>Honorius,</hi> and his Aſſociates, who own'd, as but one <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> (as <hi>Eutyches</hi> did) ſo but one <hi>Will</hi> neither.</p>
            <p>Now what was the buſineſs of all theſe zealous Fathers, but to confirm the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Creed,</hi> which had been handed, down to them from the beginning? They look't upon it to contain all things neceſſary to be believed; they reckoned it the <hi>ſaving,</hi> and the <hi>Only</hi> ſhort Rule of Faith; the Faith that is <hi>Immovable</hi> (as <hi>Ignatius</hi> the Martyr call'd it;) the <hi>unmovable</hi> and <hi>Irreformable</hi> Faith (as <hi>Tertullian;)</hi> the <hi>Perfect</hi> Faith, that <hi>unites all</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ignat. <hi>Ep. ad</hi> Smyr. Tertul. <hi>de veland. verg.</hi> Iren. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Churches throughout the whole World into one body</hi> (as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> thought;) the <hi>Right Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> Faith (as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and the reſt of the Ancients did eſteem it.) This was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why they were ſo very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious and careful to keep <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Super haec autem iidem in</hi> Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedone <hi>ſancti Patres anathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaverunt eos qui aliud Symbolum. tradiderunt aut tradunt, praeter hoc quod expoſitum eſt a trecentis decem &amp; octo ſanctis Patribus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; explanatum a centum quinquagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſanctis Patribus.</hi> Juſtinian. <hi>in Quintae Synodi</hi> Collat. <hi>prima,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil Tom. 4. part. 2. pag. 47. Edit Bin.</note> the common Creed inviolable: So that, as <hi>Juſtinain</hi> the Emperor tells us, the Fathers of the Council at <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiz'd all thoſe that <hi>had</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50211:7"/>
or <hi>do</hi> deliver any other Symbol, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that Creed of the Apoſtles, which was explained by the two firſt general Councils, that at <hi>Nice,</hi> of 318 Fathers; and the next at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> conſiſting of an hundred and fifty.</p>
            <p>I know not what the Men of <hi>Trent</hi> thought of this heavy Anathema, when they <hi>Added</hi> to the Ancient Creed a great many <hi>New</hi> Articles of their <hi>own,</hi> as equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Neceſſary</hi> to Salvation. But by this, Sir, you may ſee that the <hi>Apoſtles Symbol,</hi> as it was explicated in the firſt General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, was that and that only, which the Primitive Fathers ſo zealouſly contended to maintain; which you cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, why it ſhould have been, had not they concluded it to be a <hi>Perfect</hi> Summary. And this I note, not only to ſhew their great and moſt unreaſonable <hi>uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> who condemn all that ſtick to this Primitive Creed only: But moreover to vindicate our ſelves, who own and teach the very <hi>ſame</hi> Articles of Faith, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary principles of Chriſtianity, which was the only thing contended for by the old Catholick <hi>Fathers.</hi> Upon which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50211:7"/>
               <hi>we</hi> are no more Hereticks, than <hi>They</hi> were, our Creed being the very ſame with Theirs: So that there can be no colour of Reaſon for any to <hi>forſake</hi> our Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as if our Faith were unſound or <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective;</hi> or to be <hi>diſſatisfied</hi> in their minds, as if there were any danger of their Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, if they be but careful to <hi>adorn</hi> this Faith with a ſutable converſation.</p>
            <p>And hence I cannot but look upon it, as a ſtrange piece of weakneſs (at leaſt) in the Divines of that party, that they are ſo groſly <hi>miſtaken</hi> in their notion of of the Catholick Faith. For they quite over-look the <hi>Common Creed,</hi> as if that were not <hi>it,</hi> (whereas in Truth, that <hi>alone</hi> is the Catholick Faith;) and give that Title to the <hi>Trent-confeſſion,</hi> which is the <hi>Roman</hi> Faith only; and yet whoever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth any part of that Confeſsion, though he owns the Apoſtles Symbol, muſt be hooted at preſently as an <hi>Heretick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor can it be thought any leſs than ſtrange Inconſideration in Mr. <hi>Sclater,</hi> that he ſhould leave our Church for that of <hi>Rome,</hi> upon an Idea he hath formed in his own fancy of that Churches <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> in the Faith.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50211:8"/>
For is not <hi>our</hi> Church in moſt perfect <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> as to the Chriſtian Faith? Were the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Creed profeſt only in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, we might all go thither. But is not <hi>our</hi> Faith the ſame with <hi>Hers,</hi> in thoſe points wherein 'tis truly <hi>Primitive</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick?</hi> If Mr. <hi>Sclater</hi> can ſhew us, wherein we contradict any of thoſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſtianity, which ſo many Ancient councils confirm'd as the <hi>One Catholick</hi> Faith, we will not blame him for thinking, that we have broken the Unity thereof. But we are ſo far from offering <hi>an hundred Faiths</hi> (as he unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page.</hi> 5.</note> inſinuates) that we teach but <hi>One,</hi> and the ſame, which is <hi>Common</hi> to all the Churches in the World. Therefore his little quotations out of <hi>Ignatius, Cyprian,</hi> and the ſuppoſititious <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> are nothing at all to his purpoſe. But his Allegation out of <hi>Irenaeus (pag.</hi> 8) is groſly <hi>impertinent.</hi> For <hi>Irenaeus</hi> evidently ſpeaks of the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> and of that <hi>alone.</hi> Pray conſult the place, and ſee if <hi>Irenaeus</hi> doth not expreſly and diſtinctly repeat the ſubſtance of that Confeſsion, the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles whereof we repeat daily in our
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50211:8"/>
Churches; and then he preſently <hi>ſubjoyns,</hi> in the very next Chapter, <hi>This Doctrine and Faith the Church keeps with all care, as if ſhe dwelt in one Houſe, although ſhe be diſſeminated over the whole World. Her Faith is agreeable to theſe Doctrines, as if ſhe had one Soul, and one and the ſame Heart. Theſe Articles ſhe doth conſonantly preach, teach and deliver, as if ſhe had but one mouth. For though there be different Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, yet the Faith delivered is one and the ſame. Neither do the Churches in</hi> Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many <hi>believe or teach any other Faith, nor do thoſe Churches in</hi> Spain, <hi>nor thoſe in</hi> France, <hi>nor thoſe in the Eaſt, nor thoſe in</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, <hi>nor thoſe in</hi> Lybia, <hi>nor thoſe in the middle parts of the</hi> World<hi>: But as the Sun is one the ſame in the whole World, ſo the Doctrine of Truth every where ſhines, and enlightens all men that are willing to come to the knowledge of the Truth:</hi> He adds too (which Mr. <hi>Sclater</hi> diſingenuouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceals) <hi>that none of the Governours of the Church, though never ſuch able men, do teach any other Doctrines than theſe (for no man is above his Maſter) nor doth the weakeſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the Faith delivered: But the Creed</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:50211:9"/>
               <hi>being one and the ſame, the greateſt man doth not add more, no doth the meaneſt man believe leſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now Sir, what is all this for the advantage of the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Faith, which is <hi>ſuperadded</hi> to the Apoſtles Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol? This paſſage is ſo far from <hi>countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing,</hi> that it utterly <hi>condemns</hi> that Addition. Or what is all this againſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve &amp; teach that very <hi>ſame</hi> Faith which all Chriſtian Churches did adhere to in <hi>Irenaeus</hi> time? Or what encouragement is all this for any man to leave our Communion, as if we had violated the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the Faith? The truth is, <hi>Irenaeus</hi> &amp; the reſt of the Ancients ſaid (as we do) that Chriſt hath but <hi>one Catholick</hi> Church on Earth; that all Churches make up this Catholick Church; that they are all united in one by one common <hi>Faith,</hi> and that the Apoſtles <hi>Creed,</hi> is that one and <hi>only</hi> Faith. Now this Faith is uniformly believed by us; and therefore Mr. <hi>Sclater</hi> needed not to ſay (as he doth <hi>pag.</hi> 10.) <hi>What would I have once given to have found ſuch <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity among Proteſtants?</hi> Let him but give us our <hi>Due,</hi> and we deſire no more, and this he cannot deny without denying
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50211:9"/>
us our due, that in <hi>England, Scotland, Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, Sweedland, Geneva, Zurick,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>we have one common Creed,</hi> and the ſame which <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited all Local</hi> Churches into one <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> Church, in the Days <hi>of Old.</hi> But though we Proteſtants are United into one <hi>Faith,</hi> yet becauſe we are not United under one <hi>Pope</hi> (no more than the Primitive Churches were) Mr. <hi>Sclater</hi> leaves us. Avery ſtout Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon<hi>!</hi> If yet that be one of the <hi>True</hi> Reaſons: But by what we have ſeen of his Reaſons yet, we have ſome cauſe to believe, he hath ſome other reaſons that are ſtronger than this; ſome <hi>Reſerv'd Reaſons,</hi> among thoſe which he calls <hi>(Pag.</hi> 5.) his <hi>Reſerv'd Principles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to let Mr. <hi>Sclater</hi> go at preſent, till we meet him again. The Author of the <hi>Nubes Teſtium</hi> would perſwade you to think, that in thoſe By-opinions wherein we dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, the Primitive Fathers are on their ſide.</p>
            <p>For the clearing therefore of this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I ſhall take a very ſhort courſe; by giving you an Hiſtorical account of the Series of Affairs from the Primitive Ages, as Controverſies about theſe Points did happen to ariſe<hi>:</hi> And by this account
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50211:10"/>
you will eaſily diſcern, that our Opinions are the <hi>moſt Ancient</hi> and <hi>Catholick Opinions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the Catholick Faith had been on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd, and the Controverſie with <hi>Arius</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd at the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council about <hi>Anno</hi> 325. another Controverſie aroſe about Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, ſome Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> pretending to Supream Authority, and Univerſal Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction over the reſt. But this was clearly an Innovation<hi>:</hi> for an <hi>Ancient Canon</hi> had <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Can. Apoſtol. 34.</note> been provided (which was the Churches Rule, during the Reigns of Heathen Princes) <hi>That the Biſhops of every Country ſhould ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to him that was their Primate, and own him for their Head, and do nothing (of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) without his Approbation.</hi> By which Canon the Primacy was fixt in the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of every Province, and all Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politans throughout the World, ſtood up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame Level, and had the ſame Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Authority in their Reſpective Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictions and Countries. You cannot but ſmile to ſee what a Marginal Note there is upon this Canon in <hi>Binius</hi>'s Edition of it<hi>:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Juriſdictio E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcoporum, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terquam Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, certis &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitis limitibus circumſcripta est.</note> 
               <hi>The Juriſdiction of Biſhops (except the</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Biſhops) is Circumſcribed within certain and determinate Limits.</hi> But there is not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50211:10"/>
the leaſt ground or colour for that <hi>excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> the continual practice of the Church in thoſe times ſhews it to be a <hi>forced</hi> Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the Canon; for the Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops was <hi>limited,</hi> as all the others was; ſo that <hi>Aeneus Sylvius</hi> (afterwards Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the ſecond) inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly confeſt, that <hi>before the</hi> Nicene <hi>Council, little reſpect was had to the Church of</hi> Rome.</p>
            <p>Nor did the <hi>Nicene Council</hi> give the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Biſhops any Title to their pretended Primacy. For in the ſixth Canon of that Council the Fathers decreed, that <hi>the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Cuſtomes ſhould hold; that the Biſhop</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>of</hi> Alexandria <hi>ſhould have power over them who were in</hi> Egypt, Lybia, <hi>and</hi> Pentapolis; <hi>becauſe this was likewiſe the cuſtome for the Biſhop of</hi> Rome. <hi>Alſo that</hi> Antioch <hi>and other Provinces ſhould have the ſame Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges preſerv'd to their Churches.</hi> Whence it appears, that in thoſe times the Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Roman</hi> Patriarch was <hi>limited</hi> and <hi>bounded;</hi> and that to the <hi>Suburbicary</hi> Churches in <hi>Italy</hi> (as <hi>Ruffinus</hi> rightly underſtood that Canon.) 2. That other Provinces had the <hi>ſame</hi> equal priviledges
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50211:11"/>
within themſelves, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church had. 3. That thoſe priviledges were every where founded on ancient <hi>Cuſtomes.</hi> 4. That thoſe Cuſtomes ſhould ſtill <hi>continue</hi> in force.</p>
            <p>But all this could not bound the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of ſome Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd and hoped to <hi>enlarge</hi> their Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction by the great Intereſt they had in the (now Chriſtian) Emperors, who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt much tenderneſs to the Church in lieu of thoſe hardſhips ſhe had endured in times of Perſecution; and thought it no little Piety, out of Veneration to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to be kind to their Succeſſors<hi>:</hi> and this was one thing that by degrees brought the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> into great requeſt. Beſides, Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks and Hereticks who lay under Church-cenſures, were wont to <hi>appeal</hi> to the Emperor for redreſs, as the Donatiſts did to <hi>Conſtantine</hi> in the Pontificate of <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiades.</hi> The Emperor thinking it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for him to commit the cogniſance of Church Cauſes into the hands of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, did uſe to depute and delegate the Biſhop of his own See, with ſome more of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50211:11"/>
the Clergy, to examine the matters. And as this gave encouragement to Factious men, ever and anon to have recourſe to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo it gave encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alſo to the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croach</hi> upon the Priviledges of <hi>other</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, where ſuch cauſes ſhould regularly have been heard and determin'd in publick Synods. Yet it is obſervable, that for a long Tract of time, the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver attempted to execute their <hi>uſurped</hi> power, but ſtill they met with great <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> from thoſe who aſſerted their own Canonical <hi>Priviledges</hi> and <hi>Rights:</hi> Thus when <hi>Julius</hi> endeavoured to interpoſe in the caſe of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> who had been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly condemned by the Oriental Biſhops in the Synods of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Antioch,</hi> though <hi>Julius</hi> pretended only, that 'twas not Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonically done, but that himſelf and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Biſhops ought to have been intereſſed too in an affair of that High nature; yet <hi>Julius</hi> his <hi>appearing</hi> in this cauſe put the Oriental Biſhops into a rage, as you may ſee by his letter to them; wherein he takes notice of their <hi>Paſſion</hi> and oppoſition; and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Council. Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 391.</note> confeſſes, that they <hi>charged him with kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:50211:12"/>
               <hi>a flame of Diſcord; and that they were</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di ſunt flamina diſcordiae ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiſſe; ſi qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem id nobis in veſtris literis objicitis?</hi> Jul. <hi>Ep. Verè parem e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem in omnibus Epiſcopatibus cenſetis eſſe, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ex magnitudine civitatum (ut vos Scribitis) honorem ejus rei creſcere ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitramini.</hi> Id. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>poſitive in their Opinion, that in all Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks the Honour was really equal and the ſame, and that the Honour (much leſs the Power of a See) did not increaſe by the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Cities.</hi> This was point blank to ſtop the growth of the Pope of <hi>Romes</hi> power as a meer Uſurpation upon the Authority and Rights of other Biſhops, when yet all that <hi>Julius</hi> ſeems to have contended for, was that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his caſe might be <hi>re-conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered</hi> in a general Council, wherein he himſelf and other Weſtern Biſhops might be concern'd.</p>
            <p>But when <hi>Innocent</hi> the firſt made a try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of <hi>his</hi> skill upon the <hi>African</hi> Churches, by occaſion (as 'tis thought) of an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal made to him by <hi>Caeleſtius</hi> the <hi>Pelagian</hi> Heretick, who had been condemn'd at home in <hi>Africa;</hi> the <hi>Africans</hi> to maintain their own Priviledges, and the Canons of the Catholick Church decreed at the <hi>Mile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitan</hi> Council, that <hi>when Presbyters, Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. Milevit.</hi> cap. 22.</note> 
               <hi>or other inferiour Clergy-men did appeal from their own Biſhops, ſome neighbouring</hi> Biſhops <hi>ſhould hear the cauſe: and if they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed from them too, they ſhould not appeal,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:50211:12"/>
               <hi>but to the</hi> African <hi>Councils, or to the Primates of their own Provinces. But whoſoever ſhould appeal beyond the Sea, ſhould not be receiv'd into Communion by any in</hi> Africa. Which decree, though it ſpeaks particularly of Presbyters and Deacons, yet it reacheth Biſhops alſo; as is clear from the 31. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> Council (Three years after this) that <hi>the ſame thing againſt Appeals beyond the Sea, had been often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed concerning Biſhops too.</hi> And this cuts <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Can. Carth. 5. 31.</note> off the common ſubterfuge of the <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> who are wont to pretend, that the <hi>Milevitan</hi> Canon concern'd the <hi>inferiour</hi> Clergy onely; as if the Pope had not power of Juriſdiction over Presbyters and Deacons too, if he had any over Biſhops, eſpecially if he hath it (as they ſay) by <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all this, the Succeſſors of <hi>Innocent, (Zozimus, Boniface</hi> and <hi>Caele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine)</hi> pretended ſtill ſucceſſively to this claim of Juriſdiction in the <hi>African</hi> Churches: whereby you may ſee, what an ill uſe they made of that favour, which the Emperours ſhew'd ſome of their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors; for now inſtead of being the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50211:13"/>
               <hi>Delegates,</hi> or their Neighbours, friendly <hi>Arbitrators,</hi> they pretended to be the moſt rightful <hi>Judges</hi> of foreign cauſes.</p>
            <p>During the time of the Three foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Popes, the great caſe about Appeals to <hi>Rome</hi> was depending in <hi>Africa;</hi> and for the determining of the Controverſie, the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> Council was called, conſiſting of 217 Fathers, whereof St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> was one, <hi>Anno</hi> 419. The Pope grounded his claim of Juriſdiction upon a <hi>pretended</hi> Canon of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council: to which the <hi>Africans</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>They knew nothing of any ſuch Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, nor could find any thing to that effect in thoſe Copies they had of the Acts of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil.</hi> But being not willing either to make a Rupture in the Church, or to loſe their own Priviledges, they <hi>condeſcended</hi> to let the matter <hi>reſt,</hi> till they could procure the moſt Authentick Copies of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Canons. For which purpoſe they diſpatcht away Meſſengers to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to <hi>Antioch,</hi> and to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> ſuppoſing it impoſſible for them to miſs of the True Copies in thoſe Churches. No ſooner did they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thoſe Copies, but preſently they found
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50211:13"/>
how they had been <hi>impoſed</hi> upon by the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> for their whole pretence was a <hi>Forgery:</hi> Whereupon they <hi>confirm'd</hi> and <hi>inlarged</hi> the former <hi>Milevitan</hi> Decree, againſt <hi>any</hi> Clergy-man's appealing to the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> and to juſtifie their Acts, they ſent a Synodical Epiſtle to Pope <hi>Caeleſtine;</hi> wherein they call thoſe Appeals, <hi>Improba Refugia, Wicked Refuges;</hi> they pleaded, <hi>That no Councils had ever taken away the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Rights of the</hi> African <hi>Churches, but that the Council at</hi> Nice <hi>had left, not Presbyters onely, but all Biſhops alſo, to the Judgment of their own Metropolitans;</hi> they ſhew'd the <hi>Reaſonableneſs</hi> of this Decree, it being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for any man <hi>to be tryed ſo fairly as at home, where every man was known, and Witneſſes were ready at hand.</hi> For all this they referred themſelves to the <hi>Nicene</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, the <hi>True</hi> Copies whereof they had now <hi>received;</hi> and in the End they <hi>chid</hi> his Holineſs for his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation;</hi> earneſtly <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ne fumoſum ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phum Seculi in Eccleſiam Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti, videamur in ducere. Vide Concil. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagin. Can.</hi> 31. <hi>&amp;<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Epiſt. Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicam in fine Canonum; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Tom.</hi> 1. pag. 757.</note> exhorted him, <hi>neither to encourage ſuch Appellants to him, nor to ſend any Legates abroad in ſuch caſes, leſt it ſhould be a means of bringing (as they call it) the ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Pride of the World into the Church of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:50211:14"/>
This manifeſtly ſhews on our ſide, that the Biſhop of <hi>Romes</hi> pretence to a Primacy over the whole Chriſtian World is an <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> and <hi>incroachment</hi> upon the juſt Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Canonical Priviledges of all other Churches. And before I go on, I cannot but note it as great Weakneſs and Ignorance (for I am loath to call it a <hi>Fraud)</hi> in Mr. <hi>Sclater;</hi> who, to ſupport the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Paſtourſhip of that <hi>Italian</hi> Prelate (to whoſe <hi>Foreign</hi> power he hath ſubjected <hi>himſelf</hi> contrary to his Oaths of <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Allegiance</hi> too) cites the Canon of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, and for the Authority of them ſends us to a pretended Epiſtle of <hi>Athanaſius ad Marcum.</hi> You may <note place="margin">Pag. 12.</note> obſerve, that the Author of the <hi>Nubes Teſtium</hi> was <hi>Wiſer</hi> than to quote either thoſe <hi>Canons,</hi> or that Epiſtle; becauſe there is no Canon to that purpoſe among the Acts of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers, nor was ever ſuch a Canon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, but what was <hi>Forged</hi> and <hi>Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſititious.</hi> And as for the Epiſtle <hi>ad Marcum</hi> which goes under the name of <hi>Athanaſius;</hi> the <hi>Learned</hi> men in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have been <hi>aſhamed</hi> long ago to own its Authority, knowing it to be a <hi>Spurious</hi> piece.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50211:14"/>
               <hi>Baronius</hi> and <hi>Poſſevine</hi> both reject that E-Epiſtle; and ſo doth <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and the Abbreviator of <hi>Baronius, Henricus Sponda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellarm. de Rom. Pontif. Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 25. <hi>Spondan. ad. Anno.</hi> 325. <hi>Num.</hi> 42.</note> rejects the Epiſtle and Canons both, though Mr. <hi>Slater</hi> is pleaſed to lay ſuch ſtreſs upon them. Tis pity, that when he had thoughts of writing his Reaſons, he did not conſult ſome knowing Friend, what Authors he ſhould uſe, and what Books were <hi>Genuine,</hi> and what <hi>Spurious;</hi> for when he quoted that Epiſtle <hi>ad Marcum,</hi> and call'd it <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his, he might as well have quoted the Narrative of <hi>Titus Oates,</hi> and called it the Hiſtory of <hi>Titus Livius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to go on to our Buſineſs: Soon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe tranſactions in <hi>Africa,</hi> a General <note place="margin">Can. 8.</note> Council of 200 Fathers was held at <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> and there it was decreed again, <hi>That no Biſhop ſhould invade anothers Province, but that every Metropolitan ſhould retain his due power, and every Province ſhould have its Ancient Rights and Priviledges preſerved.</hi> Of which Decree they expreſly gave Three reaſons. 1. Leſt the Canons of the Church ſhould be tranſgreſt. 2. Leſt the Churches of Chriſt ſhould unawares loſe their Liberty. 3. Leſt the <hi>Pride of Secular Power</hi> ſhould be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50211:15"/>
brought into the Church; which was the very Reaſon and Expreſſion the <hi>Africans</hi> had uſed a little before againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments of Pope <hi>Caeleſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About Twenty years after this, a <hi>New</hi> Scene of Affairs appear'd, which is well worth your Obſervation. A great Synod of 630 Fathers met at <hi>Chalcedon:</hi> and there, notwithſtanding the Oppoſition of the Popes Legates, they confirm'd the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons that had been made at the Council of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and gave the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople, equal Honours and Priviledges with the Biſhop of Rome;</hi> meaning, not any Supremacy of <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> but <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Con.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinop. <hi>Can.</hi> 2: <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>Item Concil. Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. Can.</hi> 28.</note> an Honourable <hi>Precedency</hi> for <hi>Order</hi> ſake. The Reaſon of this was, becauſe the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial <hi>Seat</hi> was now removed to <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople:</hi> It was called, <hi>New Rome,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed the ſame civil Priviledges that the <hi>Old</hi> did: and becauſe an Honourable Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedency had been given to the Biſhop of <hi>Old Rome</hi> (not upon any pretence of a <hi>Divine right</hi> he had to it, but out of reſpect to the <hi>Imperial City,</hi> as the Fathers at <hi>Chalce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> plainly <hi>declared)</hi> therefore they thought it reaſonable, that the like Honourable precedency
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50211:15"/>
ſhould be granted to the Biſhop of <hi>New Rome</hi> alſo. Upon this there were ſtrait ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrong fears in <hi>Italy,</hi> that in a little time the <hi>Power</hi> would go along with the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour;</hi> and that the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> would carry away that Univerſal Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Juriſdiction, which ſome Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> had hitherto contended for. Now 'tis very Uſeful and Pleaſant to obſerve what a ſtrange <hi>Change</hi> this preſently wrought. For as <hi>other</hi> Chruches had hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto beſtirred themſelves againſt the pretences of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo now the very Church of <hi>Rome</hi> beſtirred her ſelf againſt the pretences of the Church of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> and with the ſame Arguments. Now the Note was <hi>alter'd</hi> on a ſudden, and even the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> were vehemently ſet againſt <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Ambition.</hi> They urg'd our Saviours precepts of <hi>Humility,</hi> and eſpecially in <hi>Biſhops:</hi> They inſiſted upon the <hi>Priviledges</hi> of all Chriſtian Churches; they ſtood ſtifly for the <hi>Canons,</hi> eſpecially for thoſe of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council (though ſome of their Predeceſſors had broken them.) So that could Authority alone for ever baffle the claim of Univerſal Paſtour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50211:16"/>
26we need uſe onely the Authority of Three Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> that in their turns undertook the Quarel with the <hi>Conſtantinopolitans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt Pope <hi>Leo</hi> engaged in it with all imaginable Zeal. He wrote to <hi>Anatolius</hi> himſelf, the then Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> rebuked him for his Inſolence and Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; pleaded the Canons againſt him; <hi>vindicated</hi> the Priviledges of all Primates; told him that every Primate <hi>ſhould keep within his own bounds, without invading the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Ep.</hi> Leonis <hi>ad</hi> Anatol. <hi>&amp; ad</hi> Marcian. <hi>&amp; ad</hi> Pulcher. <hi>&amp; ad Syn.</hi> Chalced. <hi>ex. in</hi> Binii <hi>Concil. Tom.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Rights of others,</hi> and what not? He wrote likewiſe to <hi>Marcian</hi> the Emperor, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining heavily of <hi>Anatolius for breaking the Churches peace, for violating the Decrees of the Council of</hi> Nice, and the like; and therefore deſired the Emperor to pull his Pride down. He wrote too to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs <hi>Pulcheria,</hi> accuſing <hi>Anatolius</hi> to <hi>Her</hi> alſo, and begging her aſsiſtance againſt him. He wrote to the very Synod at <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon,</hi> and told them (though they cared not for it) that he would not look upon their Acts, as to <hi>Anatolius,</hi> to be valid. Beſides all this, he wrote alſo to the Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> deſiring him likewiſe to be a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50211:16"/>
Party, and to engage the reſt of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riental Biſhops againſt <hi>Anatolius:</hi> but I do not find that they would be concern'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'twas onely an <hi>Honourary</hi> matter which was granted to the <hi>Conſtantinopolitan</hi> See, being now the <hi>Imperial Seat;</hi> and they could not but underſtand what was the bottom of <hi>Leo</hi>'s grudge.</p>
            <p>Above an Hundred years after this, it ſeems a Synod at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> gave <hi>John,</hi> the Biſhop of that place, the Title of <hi>Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumenical</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Bishop. Indeed the thing was evil, and it had grown to an Head by degrees; like a noxious <hi>Humour,</hi> that firſt <hi>gathers,</hi> then <hi>Suppurates,</hi> and at laſt comes to plain <hi>Impoſtumation.</hi> And now <hi>another</hi> Pope appear'd in the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, <hi>Pelagius</hi> the 2d. He inveigh'd bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly againſt <hi>John;</hi> and in a Letter to him charged him, with the moſt ſevere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes, <hi>to forbear that Raſh, Proud,</hi> and <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Title</hi> (as he called it.) And in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Gregor. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep.</hi> 38. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Ep.</hi> 71. <hi>item Epiſt</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagii <hi>ad Synod. in</hi> Binii <hi>Concil. Tom</hi> 2. <hi>Par.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 257. <hi>It.</hi> Gratian. <hi>decret. Pag.</hi> 303.</note> an Epiſtle to the Synod that had granted it he dealt very roundly with them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning the Title as <hi>a Deviliſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation;</hi> as <hi>injurious to the Honour of all Patriarchs, and to the power of all Biſhops, and as that</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:50211:17"/>
               <hi>which violated the</hi> Nicene <hi>Canons, and would bring the Members of Chriſt into Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very:</hi> In which particular Pope <hi>Pelagius</hi> was too much a Prophet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pelagius</hi> dying, the quarrel was left in the hands of his Succeſſor, <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great. Now he tells us, that this New Title, which <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> had U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped, <hi>Scandaliz'd all men; that all the Biſhops were inraged at it, and all their</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Greg <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep.</hi> 32, 36, 38. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Ep.</hi> 28.</note> 
               <hi>Mouths were opened againſt it;</hi> that the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church was diſquieted about it;</hi> that the <hi>peace of the Church was broken, and that the whole Church was rent in pieces by the Scandal it had given.</hi> Such great and ſtrong oppoſition did that <hi>Arrogant</hi> name preſently meet with: and yet the Title of Univerſal Biſhop was in thoſe a Title of <hi>Dignity</hi> onely, without any <hi>Power</hi> of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal <hi>Juriſdiction:</hi> It was nothing in compariſon of that which ſome have u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped a claim to <hi>Since.</hi> And if a vain <hi>Name</hi> made ſuch work in that Age, 'tis paſt imagination to conceive what cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and diſturbances would have been then throughout the whole Church, by a <hi>Newer</hi> pretence to Univerſal <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority;</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:50211:17"/>
a thing that is full of the moſt Terrible and Miſchievous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences.</p>
            <p>But of all men then living, none ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have been ſet more fiercely againſt the Title of Univerſal Biſhop, then Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> himſelf was. Concerning whom I obſerve briefly Three things. 1. That he declaimed againſt the <hi>Biſhop of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> as a <hi>Robber,</hi> as a <hi>Wolf,</hi> as an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croacher</hi> upon the Rights of all the Bishops; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Ep.</hi> 71. <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep.</hi> 32. <hi>&amp;</hi> 38. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Ep.</hi> 30.</note> as the <hi>Imitator</hi> and <hi>follower</hi> of <hi>Lucifer</hi> in his Pride, and as the <hi>Fore-runner of Antichriſt.</hi> 2. That he wrote ſeveral Letters to <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritius</hi> the Emperor, to the Bishops of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria, Antioch, Theſſalonica,</hi> and divers more, to ſtrengthen his intereſt againſt the Uſurping Patriarch, that he might take down his greatneſs before it ſwelled too High. 3. That he loaded his ill-got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Title with the moſt odious and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachful Characters he could invent, calling it a <hi>Vain, Novel, Profane, Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, Wicked, Fooliſh, Proud, Preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Name,</hi> and I know not what beſides. This was the fine <hi>Livery,</hi> wherewith he endeavoured to <hi>diſgrace</hi> his Rival, <hi>John;</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:50211:18"/>
not dreaming, I belive, that in a very ſhort time, it would be due to his own <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> and would much better <hi>become</hi> them.</p>
            <p>However we have the Judgment of no leſs then <hi>Three</hi> great Popes againſt the Title of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Biſhop: nor are we concern'd to enquire, whether they had not ſome By-ends of their own, which provoked them to uſe theſe Expreſsions. That they were unwilling any others ſhould be <hi>Partners</hi> with them in their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, is very reaſonable for us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; though I am apt to think, that <hi>Gregory</hi> ſpake his thoughts <hi>ſincerely;</hi> partly becauſe he declared ſolemnly to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, that <hi>'twas not any reſpect to his own cauſe which moved him;</hi> and partly becauſe he uſed ſo many <hi>ſevere</hi> expreſsions to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the thing <hi>it ſelf</hi> Invidious and Odious; which a man ſo zealous for the Honour of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair, as <hi>Gregory</hi> was, would not have done, had he but dream't of <hi>His,</hi> or his <hi>Succeſſors</hi> having that Title<hi>:</hi> 'Tis not like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that he would wittingly have branded himſelf or his See, with ſo many <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>gly</hi> and <hi>Infamous</hi> Characters.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:50211:18"/>
The true account of it therefore ſeems to be this. Some <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops longed for Superiority over the other Churches, and might <hi>Hope</hi> in time to accompliſh their deſires. But in <hi>Gregory</hi>'s days, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what before, <hi>Rome</hi> began mightily to ſink, by the great Oppreſsion of the <hi>Lombards,</hi> and by the Tranſlation of the Imperial Seat. <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> flouriſht at a great rate<hi>:</hi> the Court was there: the Emperor favour'd it<hi>:</hi> the Patriarch of it had now gotten a very High Title; and the Bishops of <hi>Rome</hi> might fear, that Univerſal <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> would follow by degrees, and that their Cauſe was <hi>going apace.</hi> Therefore they might think it in vain for them to <hi>ſmother and conceal</hi> the truth any longer; &amp; ſo to be <hi>Revenged</hi> upon the growing Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch, they ſpeak at laſt their thoughts <hi>freely.</hi> In ſhort, if theſe Three Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> where <hi>ſincere</hi> in what they ſaid, their memory is the more valuable for aſſerting the Truth<hi>:</hi> if they looked upon any Siniſter ends of their own, the <hi>Glory</hi> of Truth is the greater, for being juſtified even by thoſe who were no friends to it.</p>
            <p>You will perhaps wonder now, how
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50211:19"/>
this Title ſhould go <hi>unexpectly</hi> and ſo <hi>ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly</hi> from <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to <hi>Rome?</hi> For it was obtained of the Uſurper <hi>Phocas</hi> by <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niface</hi> the 3<hi>d.</hi> who was the next Succeſſor (but <hi>one)</hi> to that <hi>Gregory,</hi> who had <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned</hi> the Title with ſo much bitterneſs. Why, thus it was in ſhort<hi>: Phocas</hi> had barbarouſly Murther'd his Prince, <hi>Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> the Emperour, and his Children. <hi>Cyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acus</hi> then Bishop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> hated and oppos'd him for his execrable Villany. <hi>Boniface</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> preſently ſtrikes in, makes uſe of this Opportunity, ſues for the Title of Univerſal Bishop, hoping now to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the <hi>Church,</hi> by the help of a <hi>Tyrant</hi> that had invaded the <hi>State;</hi> and <hi>Phocas</hi> grants his requeſt, partly out of Hatred to his enemy <hi>Cyriacus;</hi> partly, for fear leſt <hi>Boniface</hi> ſhould raiſe up ſome evil againſt him in the Weſt; and partly too, becauſe he ſaw, the Bishops of <hi>Rome,</hi> were ready to crouch and <hi>ſneak</hi> to him, though a bloudy <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> as long as they could gain any thing by their baſe Submiſsion; of which he found a plain experiment in <hi>Gregory</hi> himſelf, who wrote a flattering Letter to him, which begins thus, <hi>Gloria in excelſis,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:50211:19"/>
               <hi>&amp;c. Glory to God in the higheſt;</hi> and ſo he goes on, <hi>Let the Heavens rejoyce, and the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Greg. <hi>Regiſt. Lib.</hi> 11. <hi>Ep.</hi> 38. <hi>aa</hi> Phocam.</note> 
               <hi>Earth be glad, and let all the People that have hitherto been much afflicted, be chearful for your kind actions.</hi> This he thought might very well <hi>Merit</hi> ſomething at the hands of <hi>Phocas;</hi> and ſo <hi>Boniface</hi> obtain'd the Title of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Biſhop; and that too juſt about the time when <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſtept into <hi>Chriſtendom; then</hi> it was that Oppreſſion got into the <hi>Church;</hi> God pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing the <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Factions</hi> of Chriſtians with <hi>Two</hi> Scourges at once, which ever ſince have made the Chriſtian World to Smart ſeverely.</p>
            <p>By this account you may ſee the Riſe and Progreſs of the Popes Supremacy: What an <hi>Innovation</hi> it is, and how ſtrongly it was oppoſed by the Catholick Church in the Primitive times for above 200 years together after it was firſt pretended to<hi>:</hi> Before I paſs from this Topick, I ſhall lay hold on this opportunity to ſatisfie you touching thoſe Allegations, which the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Nubes Teſtium</hi> hath collected, to prove (if he could) that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> has the Primacy over the whole
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50211:20"/>
World, and that by <hi>Divine Right</hi> too, and by Commiſſion granted him by Chriſt himſelf in the Perſon of St. <hi>Peter.</hi> Now I obſerve in general, that this Author hath wholly <hi>omitted</hi> that Hiſtorical account which has been now given you, becauſe it evidently clears the point againſt him; but inſtead of that, he has pickt up ſome ends &amp; ſhreds out of ſome of the Ancients, which may ſeem Specious to <hi>Ignorant</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but ſignifies nothing with a man that is rightly acquainted with the Series of the Controverſie. Whereas he pretends to give us an Hiſtory of the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> of the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> of <hi>Berengarius,</hi> of the <hi>Iconoclaſts, &amp;c.</hi> (which I ſhall take notice of hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.) he takes no notice at all of thoſe <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> and <hi>Councils</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> and the Eaſt, which reſiſted the firſt incroachments that tended to the introduction of an Uſurped Supremacy. He knew, that ſuch an Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory would burn his Fingers, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thought fit, not ſo much as to <hi>touch</hi> it; but throws the whole matter, and that very briefly, upon the <hi>Donatiſts;</hi> as if the <note place="margin">Pag. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Donatiſts</hi> were the onely men that denyed the Popes Supremacy, and broke with him
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50211:20"/>
upon that account: whereas indeed the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> were <hi>They,</hi> who gave the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> the firſt unlucky <hi>occaſion</hi> to claim Juridicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out of their due bounds, by their <hi>Appeals</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and by their running from their proper Judges in <hi>Africk;</hi> witneſs their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals in the Papacy of <hi>Melchiades.</hi> So that it was not thoſe <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> that were the <hi>firſt</hi> or the <hi>onely</hi> men that oppoſed the Popes Uſurpations, but the Catholick <hi>Fathers,</hi> who were forced to ſtand up in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of their own juſt priviledges.</p>
            <p>Now it is not imaginable, that any of the Fathers would (eſpecially during that Controverſie) ſay any thing that might really ſerve to ſtrengthen the unlawful pretences of the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> againſt themſelves: and therefore you may very ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally conclude, that thoſe paſſages which are gather'd out of the Fathers in favour of the Popes Supream Authority, are forced &amp; wreſted to a ſence which they cannot natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally bear. But to examine particulars:</p>
            <p>If you pleaſe to peruſe (for 'tis tedious to Tranſcribe) all the Authorities this Man cites, you will find that they are concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Four things<hi>:</hi> 1. Concerning thoſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50211:21"/>
high <hi>Characters</hi> which ſome of the Ancients gave of <hi>S. Peter</hi> himſelf. 2. Concerning thoſe honourable <hi>Titles</hi> which they gave to the Biſhops and See of <hi>Rome</hi> 3. Concerning thoſe <hi>Applications</hi> which were ſometimes made to the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> upon emergent occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. 4. Concerning the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> upon ſuch <hi>Applications.</hi> And upon a full and impartial conſideration of theſe ſeveral things, you will eaſily find, what falſe grounds they go upon, who endeavour ſo eagerly from theſe Obſervations to prove the Univerſal ſupream power of the Pope, eſpecially by <hi>Divine Right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Theſe Authorities are concerning the high <hi>Characters,</hi> which ſome of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents gave of <hi>S. Peter</hi> himſelf; as that he was the <hi>Prince,</hi> the <hi>Head</hi> of the Apoſtles, and the like. Now what doth this mean, but that S. <hi>Peter</hi> was the moſt <hi>Eminent</hi> Apoſtle, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his <hi>age,</hi> in reſpect of his <hi>zeal,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his <hi>couragious Profeſſions</hi> of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and <hi>Love</hi> to his Maſter, in reſpect of the <hi>Precedency</hi> he might have for <hi>Order-ſake,</hi> and in reſpect too of the <hi>Honour</hi> he had in <hi>Founding</hi> Chriſt's Church; for the Firſt Converts were made by his Preaching,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:50211:21"/>
'Twas he that gather'd at once thoſe <hi>Three thouſand Souls,</hi> which were call'd, <hi>The Church,</hi> Act. 2. 42; and becauſe he was the firſt Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Church, he was very fitly called a <hi>Rock;</hi> But doth all this import, that he was above all the other Apoſtles in <hi>Power?</hi> Or that he had Supream <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> over them? S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks twice of the <hi>very chiefeſt Apoſtles:</hi> and what if S. <hi>Peter</hi> was the chiefeſt of all? Doth it follow that he was the chiefeſt in <hi>Authority?</hi> No, S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s power was as great as His; and therefore he ſaith in one place. <hi>I was not a whit behind the very chiefeſt Apoſtles,</hi> 2 Cor. 11. 15. and in another place, <hi>in nothing am I behind the very chiefeſt Apoſtles,</hi> 2 Cor. 12. 11. So the Ancients allow'd <hi>S. Peter</hi> a <hi>preheminence</hi> of <hi>Honor,</hi> but not a <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy</hi> of <hi>Power;</hi> as 'tis clear from that ſingle paſſage which our Author cites out of <hi>S. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> (and I wonder he did not better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it) <hi>As</hi> Plato <hi>was Prince of the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 34.</note> 
               <hi>ſo was</hi> Peter, <hi>of the Apoſtles.</hi> Had <hi>Plato</hi> any Authority or Juriſdiction over the Reſt? No; all that is meant is, that <hi>Plato</hi> was the moſt <hi>Eminent</hi> and <hi>Renowned</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher. <hi>S. Gregory</hi> call'd <hi>Peter</hi> the <hi>chief</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Greg: <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep.</hi> 38.</note> 
               <hi>Member of the Holy and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church:</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:50211:22"/>
and (ſaith he) <hi>Paul, Andrew</hi> and <hi>John, What were They but the Heads of particular Churches?</hi> If the word <hi>Head</hi> always imports <hi>Authority;</hi> then had thoſe three Apoſtles as much Authority over <hi>Peter,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> had over <hi>Them.</hi> But the Truth is, the Ancients ever thought, <hi>all the Apoſtles had authority alike:</hi> And ſo St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> (for inſtance) tells us, that <hi>what</hi> Peter <hi>was, that were the reſt of the Apoſtles too, endued with an equal Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerſhip</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoc erant u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique &amp; ceteri Apoſtoli, quod fuit</hi> Petrus, <hi>pari conſortio praediti &amp; honoris &amp; potestatis. S.</hi> Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian. <hi>de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit. Eccleſ. Ep. ad. Quintum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in Honour and Power.</hi> And elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where he ſaith plainly, that <hi>Peter,</hi> whom the Lord choſe firſt, and on whom he built his Church, in his diſpute with <hi>Paul</hi> about Circumciſion, <hi>did not inſolently claim, or arrogantly aſſume any thing to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as if he held the Primacy, or ought to be obeyed rather then thoſe Diſciples who were called after him.</hi> Whence it is clear, that though ſome of the Ancients ſtyled him the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Head</hi> of the Apoſtles, yet they did not aſcribe to him any Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour <hi>Authority</hi> or <hi>Power,</hi> but onely an <hi>Honorary Precedency,</hi> like that which is given to the Chair-man of a <hi>Committee,</hi> who is above the reſt in <hi>Eminence,</hi> but in <hi>Power</hi> the ſame with the reſt, that are equally and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:50211:22"/>
jointly in Commiſſion with him. And thus all our Authors <hi>Collections</hi> touching St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s great <hi>Characters,</hi> are anſwer'd in ſhort.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Other of his Authorities are concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thoſe Honourable <hi>Titles,</hi> which ſome of the Ancients gave to the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> as that There was <hi>the moſt potent Principality</hi> (or, the Imperial Seat of the Emperor) that <hi>the Firſt Chair, and the principal Church was There,</hi> that it was the <hi>Head Church,</hi> that the Biſhop of it was a <hi>Great Paſtour,</hi> and the <hi>Head,</hi> to whom Antiquity had <hi>Given a Prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of Prieſthood</hi> (or, <hi>the Precedency</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all other Biſhops.) And what is all this, and Ten times more, to the Popes pretended Authority over all Churches, and all Biſhops, and that by <hi>Divine Right</hi> too? Antiquity <hi>beſtowed</hi> upon the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> a <hi>Preheminence,</hi> ſaith our Author out <note place="margin">Pag. 45.</note> of the Emperor <hi>Valentinian</hi>'s Letter: and who doubts it? But it was nothing but a <hi>Civil Reſpect,</hi> and an Honourable, yet vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary <hi>Deference</hi> to him, becauſe he was Biſhop of the <hi>Chief City,</hi> and was near the Emperor, and was capable of doing the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50211:23"/>
Catholick Church (by his Intereſt in the Emperor) more good Offices, then other Biſhops could do; therefore they were willing to <hi>Complement</hi> him with great <hi>Titles,</hi> and to give him the upper hand, and the precedency, for <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Peace-ſake. To the Epiſcopal Chair at Old Rome, becauſe it was</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Concil. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</hi> Can. 8.</note> 
               <hi>the Imperial City, the Fathers very fitly gave an Honourable preheminence,</hi> as thoſe 630 Fathers profeſt at the Council of <hi>Chalcedon;</hi> But this was a Frank-gift, a voluntary <hi>Act,</hi> and <hi>Courteſie</hi> of the Catholick Church; and from theſe Reſpectful compellations and Honorary Grants of <hi>Precedency,</hi> to argue, that the Biſhop and See of <hi>Rome</hi> had <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> over the reſt, is the ſame thing as if you ſhould ſay, that becauſe among our <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> the Mayor of <hi>London</hi> hath the Title of <hi>Lord,</hi> therefore all other Majors and Headboroughs are under his <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand:</hi> Or, becauſe among our Cities, <hi>London</hi> is the Chief and Head-city, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all other Cities and Corporations are under its <hi>Juriſdiction:</hi> Or, becauſe among our <hi>Peer</hi>'s there is a <hi>Primier</hi> Duke, or a <hi>Firſt</hi> Earl, therefore all other Peers are in <hi>ſubjection</hi> to him<hi>:</hi> Or, becauſe amongſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50211:23"/>
our <hi>Biſhopricks</hi> that of <hi>Durham</hi> hath ſome ſingular Favours granted to it, therefore the Prelate of that Dioceſs is in his Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Power and Authority <hi>Superior</hi> to all the reſt. The Ancients did not begrudge that fair <hi>Preheminence,</hi> which upon the New moduling of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire they found it neceſſary for them to give to ſome Patriarch or other, and for ſome ſpecial Reaſons thought it beſt and moſt proper for them to give to the Patriarch of <hi>Rome;</hi> but they did not give away their own Authority, or that Power they had at home, in reſpect whereof all Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops were his <hi>Equals:</hi> No, ſaith St. <hi>Cyprian, The Epiſcopal Authority is one and the ſame,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſcopatus unus eſt, cujus a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis in ſolidum pars tenetur. S.</hi> Cyprian <hi>de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitate Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>whereof all particular Biſhops are equal and joint-poſſeſſors, like joint-Heirs in Fee.</hi> And St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> (whom our Author cites) ſaith clearly againſt him, that <hi>though the Biſhop</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 41.</note> 
               <hi>of</hi> Rome <hi>had the Preheminence, yet the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal power was common to all that were of that Function:</hi> and therefore <hi>Optatus</hi> call'd Pope <hi>Siricius</hi> his <hi>Fellow; Socius,</hi> is the word (which our Author hath very igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly, or very diſingenuouſly rendred, <hi>Contemporary;</hi> but the plain meaning is) our
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:50211:24"/>
               <hi>Fellow, or Equal.</hi> The Ancients diſtinguiſht between <hi>Priority</hi> in point of <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy</hi> or <hi>Primacy</hi> in point of <hi>Juriſdiction.</hi> The former they denyed not the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> but when once he went about to take advantage by their free conceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to incroach upon their due privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, they reſolutely oppoſed his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations,</hi> though at the ſame time they gave him an <hi>Honourable</hi> deference. This was the ground of that Controverſie whereof I have given you a ſhort account; and for your further ſatisfaction you may conſult the vehement Epiſtles of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> to the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> and particularly that to <hi>Cornelius,</hi> where he ſtoutly defends the priviledges of foreign Churches and their Right of judging matters at home, againſt all Appeals to the <hi>Roman</hi> See; and if anything be needful to be added, it ſhall be onely what St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaid afterwards at <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neque enim quiſquam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> ſe Epiſcopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituit, aut Tyrannico terrore ad obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendi neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem collegas ſuos adigit, &amp;c.</hi> Cyprian. <hi>de baptizand. Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. in initie.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> Council; <hi>None of us makes himſelf a Biſhop of Biſhops, or by any Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Threats, compelleth his Colleagues to a neceſſity of Obedience; in regard that every Biſhop hath by vertue of his own Liberty and Authority, a Power of Judgment in himſelf,</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:50211:24"/>
               <hi>and can no more be judged by another Biſhop, than another Biſhop can be judged by him.</hi> This he ſpake <hi>deſignedly</hi> againſt the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> and if you conſider the place, you will find it to be ſuch a pregnant Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony againſt the pretended Supremacy of the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> as I believe the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Nubes Teſtium</hi> will be puzled how to anſwer.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Next we are to conſider thoſe his Quotations which relate to thoſe <hi>Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> which Foreigners were wont to make to the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop upon ſpecial <hi>Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> and examine whether theſe did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and argue that Supremacy, which 'tis pretended he had in the Primitive Ages. 1. Then 'tis true, that other Biſhops were anciently wont to acquaint the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> with the ſtate of Church-affairs in their ſeveral Provinces; eſpecially if any new thing hapned. And this was all that the <hi>Sardican</hi> Fathers meant, when writing to Pope <hi>Julius,</hi> who had excuſed himſelf for his abſence from the Synod, in regrad they had accepted his excuſe, they ſent him an account of what they had done; <hi>becauſe they thought it moſt proper for the</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:50211:25"/>
               <hi>Biſhops from ſeveral Provinces to relate or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate their proceedings to the Head,</hi> that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Si ad</hi> Petri <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtoli ſedem, de ſingulis provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciis domini refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Sacerdotes.</hi>
               </note> is, to St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>See</hi> (the ſence of which place our Author hath perverted by rendring it ſo, as if they thought it beſt for them to <note place="margin">Pag. 25.</note> have <hi>recourſe</hi> to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome:</hi> an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt innuendo,</hi> that he was not ſo much their <hi>Brother</hi> as their <hi>Judge.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what can any man get by this, that the Biſhops in thoſe times would not keep one another in <hi>Ignorance?</hi> In order to the Peace and Unity of the Catholick Church, it was abſolutely neceſſary for them to hold a <hi>mutual, brotherly, correſpondence:</hi> And why ſhould they paſs by one that was Biſhop of ſo eminent a City as <hi>Rome</hi> was? Yet this is no argument of any <hi>Authority</hi> he had over them for he was wont to do the ſame thing himſelf; as other Biſhops com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated the affairs of their provinces to <hi>him,</hi> ſo he communicated the affairs of his Province to <hi>Them</hi> too; and ſo, this is no more an argument for the Authority of the <hi>one,</hi> than 'tis for the Authority of all the <hi>reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is true too, that the Primitive Fathers did many times <hi>conſult</hi> the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:50211:25"/>
of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> in points that were controverted and good reaſon they had to do ſo; for the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was then <hi>uncorrupt;</hi> men of great Learning and Note flockt thither, ſome out of <hi>curioſity,</hi> and ſome upon <hi>buſineſs;</hi> becauſe, <hi>Rome</hi> was the chief Seat of the Empire (which is the Genuine ſence of <hi>Iraenus,</hi> as he is cited <note place="margin">Pag. 22.</note> by our Author) And where was any Controverſie ſo likely to be determin'd, as at <hi>Rome?</hi> But what of all this? Doth it follow hence, that they lookt upon the Pope as the ſupream <hi>Judge?</hi> You know, many of the <hi>Reformers</hi> did either go or ſend to <hi>Geneva,</hi> to conſult <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi>'s Opinion; but did any of them think, they were under his <hi>Juriſdiction?</hi> This is as ſtrong an Argument on the behalf of the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> for the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy of their Pope, as 'tis on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the behalf of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> for the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy of the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi> And yet we would not take away any of his <hi>due</hi> Honour from him<hi>:</hi> Let him cleanſe his Church from thoſe Errors and Corruptions we juſtly complain of;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:50211:26"/>
let him keep within his own bounds, without invading the Liberties of other Churches, and the Rights of Princes; let him make <hi>Rome</hi> the Seat of true Piety and Literature: let him be, as he ſhould be, like a right Primitive Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch; and then he ſhall ſee whether we will not give him the ſame <hi>deference,</hi> that the Primitive Chriſtians did.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is true alſo, that foreign Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops were wont, as occaſion did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, to give the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> an account of their <hi>Faith.</hi> But what then? Did they not give the ſame account to the <hi>whole Church,</hi> and to <hi>other</hi> Biſhops, as well as to the <hi>Roman?</hi> It was a <hi>common Cauſe;</hi> and every Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop was deeply concern'd to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, whether ſuch as were of the ſame <hi>Order,</hi> were ſound in the ſame Catholick Faith. And therefore when they were newly <hi>Ordain'd,</hi> or were at any time <hi>ſuſpected</hi> of Errors, they were oblig'd to ſatisfie all their Fellow-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and did often give an account of their Faith, under their hands for the ſatisfaction of the whole Church.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50211:26"/>
Nay 'tis notorious that even the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> did the <hi>ſame</hi> thing (and ſome of them were <hi>commanded</hi> to it in open Synods) and the Learned and Moderate Archbishop of <hi>Paris, Petrus de Marca,</hi> ingenuouſly tells us, <hi>That</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pet. <hi>de Marca de Concord. Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>'twas uſual in thoſe times for a Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch, and for the very Biſhop of</hi> Rome, <hi>when he was newly choſen, to ſend Letters abroad concerning his Ordination; to which was added a Profeſſion of his Faith.</hi> So that 'tis impertinent what our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor <note place="margin">Pag. 28.</note> alledgeth, of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria</hi> giving his Name-ſake of <hi>Rome,</hi> a Declaration of his <hi>Faith;</hi> for if this was an argument of his ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the <hi>Pope,</hi> it is as ſtrong a proof, that the Pope himſelf was in ſubjection to other <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Nor is it to any more purpoſe, what our Author has collected touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Popes hearing of Plantiffs <hi>Cauſes,</hi> though he ſeems to lay a great deal of ſtreſs upon it. For what the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> did of this kind, he did either as the Emperors <hi>Delegate,</hi> or as an indifferent <hi>Referee,</hi> or as a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:50211:27"/>
friendly <hi>Neighbour,</hi> whoſe Mediation and interceſſion in foreign parts (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when other Biſhops <hi>concurr'd</hi> with him, as commonly they were wont) might and did go a great way towards the Righting of thoſe who were ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to have been unjuſtly or hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dealt with at home. But that Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications were made to him upon this ground, that he was the <hi>ſole Head</hi> of the Catholick Church, and ſo might by virtue of his unlimited Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial power, command Redreſſes to be made in any caſe, upon his own hearing of it, is more than our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hath as yet proved, or is able to prove with the help of all his friends. And for the clearing of this, I ſhall, 1. Give our Author a <hi>General</hi> anſwer; And then, 2. Conſider the <hi>particulars,</hi> touching the <hi>Applications</hi> made to the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Euſtathius Sebaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> by <hi>Athanaſius, Chryſoſtome,</hi> and others, whoſe caſes he is pleaſed to inſtance in.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then in general, it is certain that every mans Cauſe was in thoſe times
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:50211:27"/>
to be heard and determin'd in his own <hi>Province,</hi> without any Liberty given him to appeal to any <hi>foreign</hi> Biſhop whatſoever, as to a ſuperiour <hi>Judge.</hi> This is proved already by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Hiſtorical account<hi>:</hi> but for your further ſatisfaction I ſhall referr you to the Learned Writer <hi>Petrus de Marca</hi> himſelf, whoſe obſervations had our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor read and conſidered, he would hardly have collected any thing of this nature, unleſs he had deſigned to abuſe and impoſe upon his Readers <hi>Ignorance.</hi> For that Learned Writer doth of ſet purpoſe prove theſe Seven things, which utterly over-throw what the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Nubes Teſtium</hi> drives at. 1. That all Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical <hi>were anciently</hi> determined by Definitive and Decretory ſentences in Provincial <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Concord. Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. 2, &amp;c.</note> as the ſupream Authority. 2. That when an <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> perſon thought himſelf wronged by a Povincial Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, though he had no power of <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing</hi> from it, yet he might uſe his endeavours to get the actions of the Synod <hi>review'd.</hi> For that great man
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:50211:28"/>
doth excellently diſtinguiſh between an <hi>Appeal,</hi> and a <hi>Review.</hi> An <hi>Appeal</hi> (ſaith he) is, <hi>when a Cauſe is entirely removed to the Cogniſance of a ſuperior Judge; but a Review is, when the Judgment of a Cauſe is left to the ſame Court to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard and re-conſidered, ſome other Judges being joined with thoſe, who before paſt the Definitive ſentence, for the reverſing of it, in caſe upon a review, there appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed new and ſufficient reaſons for it.</hi> 3. That in order to ſuch a <hi>review,</hi> Applications were wont to be made to the Emperor <hi>himſelf,</hi> until the time of the <hi>Sardican</hi> Synod, which was about Twenty years after that at <hi>Nice.</hi> 4. That though the <hi>Sardican</hi> Synod allowed Applications to be made to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> (out of reſpect, as I ſuppoſe, to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors <hi>quiet,</hi> and to ſave him a great deal of <hi>trouble</hi> and <hi>vexation)</hi> yet they gave him no power to <hi>decide</hi> or <hi>hear</hi> the Cauſe himſelf, but onely that power of ordering a <hi>review,</hi> which the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors had. 5. That the Synod which <hi>granted</hi> the Pope this power, conſiſted but of Eighty <hi>Weſtern</hi> Biſhops. 6. That
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:50211:28"/>
even this <hi>little</hi> power thus freely <hi>given</hi> by thoſe <hi>few</hi> men, was not grounded upon any <hi>right</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had to it, either from <hi>Scripture,</hi> or <hi>Canon,</hi> or ſo much as <hi>Cuſtome, but a thing</hi> of <hi>Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie</hi> onely; and therefore it was put to the <hi>Vote</hi> in that Synod by <hi>Hoſius</hi> and <hi>Gaudentius, If it pleaſe you, if it ſeem</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 <hi>Synod. Sardic.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>good unto you, let us grant unto the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of</hi> Rome, <hi>out of reſpect to St.</hi> Peter<hi>'s Memory,</hi> &amp;c. 7. That theſe Canons of the <hi>Sardican</hi> Synod were not receiv'd in the <hi>Oriental</hi> Churches, which ſtill ſtood ſtifly to it, that neither the Bishop of <hi>Rome.</hi> nor any other Bishops of the Weſt had any thing to do with the proceedings in the Eaſt, ſo as to over-rule thoſe Determinations which were made in Provincial Synods. Theſe things are ſo ſtrongly and evidently proved by <hi>Petrus de Marca</hi> himſelf, that every man of ſenſe muſt reſt ſatisfied in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous account he has given touching this point. And therefore, though our Author pretends by his Collections to prove, that in thoſe ancient Times the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> had an unlimited
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:50211:29"/>
power over <hi>Synods,</hi> ſo that he could <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcind</hi> their actions <hi>Authoritatively,</hi> and as a ſupream <hi>Judge,</hi> yet what he ſaith, is nothing but <hi>Banter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. As for thoſe particular <hi>caſes,</hi> which he hath inſtanced in, if you conſider them rightly, you may eaſily diſcover the fallacy. For what if <hi>Euſtathius Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſtenus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad Annum.</hi> 365. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> applyed himſelf to Pope <hi>Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius?</hi> Doth this argue that he lookt upon him as the ſupream <hi>Judge?</hi> No ſurely; for it is notorious, and <hi>Sponda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> himſelf doth acknowledge it, that he applyed himſelf alſo to ſeveral other Bishops in <hi>Italy, France, Africk, Sicily,</hi> and <hi>Illyricum,</hi> and that with Letters from all theſe he addreſt himſelf to the Synod at <hi>Tyana,</hi> for his reſtitution to his Biſhoprick: So that according to this rate, a great many other Biſhops were ſupream <hi>Heads</hi> of the Church, as well as the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the caſe of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> what if he applyed himſelf to Pope <hi>Julius,</hi> when he had been unjuſtly caſt out of his Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick by his enemies at the <hi>Tyrian</hi> Synod? Our Author doth acknowledge
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:50211:29"/>
out of <hi>Sozomen,</hi> that <hi>Julius ſent</hi> for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius</hi> to <hi>Rome, becauſe 'twas not ſafe for him to continue in</hi> Egypt<hi>:</hi> and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not you invite any diſtreſſed man to your Houſe for protection, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently you muſt be his <hi>Judge?</hi> Again; what if <hi>Julius</hi> did afterwards cite <hi>him</hi> and his <hi>Adverſaries</hi> to appear at <hi>Rome?</hi> This is no argument that he was by his Place and Office ſupream over all, but that he was onely an indifferent <hi>Referee</hi> in that particular Cauſe. For <hi>Petrus de Marca</hi> himſelf doth tell us, that the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riental Biſhops, who had depoſed <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius, did by joint Conſent refer the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viewing of the whole matter</hi> to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> and yet not to him onely, but to a Synod of Weſtern Biſhops together <hi>with</hi> him; and that Pope <hi>Julius</hi> called a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod at the requeſt of thoſe who were <hi>Legates</hi> from the Oriental Biſhops<hi>:</hi> So that all this was nothing but an <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration;</hi> nor was the Pope <hi>ſole</hi> Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor neither, but a great many other Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops too were deſired to be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mpires</hi> with him, becauſe it was unreaſonable that ſo great a man as <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:50211:30"/>
of ſo eminent a See as <hi>Alexandria</hi> was, ſhould be deprived of his rights by a Factious party after a clandeſtine manner. For the removing of this Scandal, the whole buſineſs was by <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Agreement</hi> left to the conſideration of a Synod at <hi>Rome;</hi> which argues not at all, that the <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>They</hi> had an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent Authority to Judge in that caſe; no more than it argues, that every ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect number of <hi>Referees</hi> and Arbitrators in <hi>London,</hi> have the decretive power of my Lord Chancellor in <hi>Weſtminſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall onely add, that our Author hath <hi>perverted</hi> the ſenſe of Pope <hi>Julius,</hi> in tranſlating his Epiſtle<hi>:</hi> For whereas he renders it thus, <hi>Are you ignorant, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the receiv'd Cuſtome, you ought firſt to have writ to us, that hence what was juſt might have been determin'd;</hi> it ought to be tranſlated according to the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of the words in the <hi>Greek</hi> Copy, thus; <hi>Are you ignorant that this is the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, firſt to write to us, that ſo afterwards things which are juſt may be determin'd.</hi> Whence it appears, that all the right
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:50211:30"/>
which the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> claimed to the Complement of an <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> was grounded upon meer <hi>Cuſtome;</hi> and that the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his caſe did belong not to him onely, but to <hi>other</hi> Biſhops alſo, that Right might be done him (not <hi>hence,</hi> or from <hi>Rome,</hi> but) <hi>afterwards,</hi> by the <hi>concurrence</hi> and <hi>common</hi> Suffrage of all. And therefore <hi>Petrus de Marca</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends Cardinal <hi>Perron,</hi> for abuſing Pope <hi>Julius,</hi> and for <hi>perverting</hi> and <hi>wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting</hi> his ſenſe, after the ſame fallacious manner, as our Author has done: And <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De concord. Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>C.</hi> 4. § 8.</note> for his reprehenſion I referr him to that excellent Writer.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not need to detain you with a long anſwer to what he ſaith concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Paul</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 30.</note> of <hi>Ancyra,</hi> and the reſt, who were ejected as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> was. For their caſe was the <hi>ſame</hi> with his; and ſeveral Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops (and the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> among others) were pitcht upon by the <hi>Conſent</hi> of all <hi>Parties</hi> to re handle it; and <hi>impowered</hi> (as <hi>Petrus de Marca</hi> doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs) to ſend for them to <hi>Rome,</hi> for the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> § 2.</note> re-examination thereof: and all this
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:50211:31"/>
doth amount to no more, than a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and neighbourly <hi>Reference.</hi> I ſhall onely note, that the Eaſtern Biſhops were ſo far from owning any Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Pope to <hi>decide</hi> the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie himſelfe, that becauſe he preſumed ſo much as to receive <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and the reſt into his Communion, before the Cauſe had been determin'd in a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod of Weſtern and Eaſtern Biſhops too, they fell out with him horribly, and grew out ragious, as you may ſee in their Synodical Epiſtle, in <hi>Binius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much like to this was the Caſe of St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> which our Author doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in too, as if St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> being unjuſtly depos'd by <hi>Theophilus</hi> of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> had <hi>Appealed</hi> to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> as the ſupream <hi>Judge.</hi> But the vanity of all this is ſufficiently proved by the ingenuous <hi>Petrus de Marca,</hi> who beſtowes a whole Chapter upon this caſe onely; where he ſhews, that St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De concord. Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Cap.</hi> 9.</note> appeal'd, not to the <hi>Pope,</hi> but to a general <hi>Council;</hi> that he wrote indeed to the Pope, but not to him <hi>onely,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the Biſhops of <hi>Milan</hi> and <hi>Aquilea;</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:50211:31"/>
that the end of his writing was, that the <hi>Italian</hi> Biſhops would <hi>conſent</hi> to the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a <hi>Council,</hi> and would help to perſwade the Emperors to call one, and that nothing can be drawn from St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>'s caſe to prove the Popes Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy. And the Truth is, St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome diſown'd</hi> the Juriſdiction of a foreign Biſhop, as you may eaſily ſee by his Epiſtle to Pope <hi>Innocent.</hi> Therefore our Author <hi>falſifies</hi> the ſenſe of St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chryſ. <hi>Epiſt. ad Innocent. Tom</hi> 7. <hi>pag.</hi> 154. Ed. Savil.</note> for towards the end of that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle he ſpeaks, not to <hi>Innocent</hi> onely, but to <hi>other</hi> Biſhops of <hi>Italy too, calling them his moſt honoured and Religious Lords:</hi> and that which he deſires of them all, is, that they would write to <hi>Theophilus</hi> and the reſt, to <hi>convince</hi> them, and <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> let them know <hi>that ſuch irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar proceedings as had been car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on by a Party againſt</hi> Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom, <hi>when he was</hi> abſent, <hi>and did not decline a fair Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, ought to be lookt upon</hi> as <hi>null</hi> and <hi>void,</hi> as <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they were in their own nature; and that ſuch men ought to ſuffer according to</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:50211:32"/>
               <hi>the Eccleſiaſtical Laws.</hi> To which he adds a further requeſt, that <hi>Innocent</hi> and the reſt of his brother-Biſhops <hi>would own him for a Brother; that he might receive com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municatory Letters from them, and have their love, and the love of all others, as formerly he had.</hi> And what is all this to the ſupream and ſole <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> of the Pope over all other Biſhops? Suppoſe ſome eminent Divine of a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Church abroad in <hi>Denmark,</hi> or elſewhere, ſhould now be in St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>'s hard caſe, and ſhould ſend to my Lord of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, to declare their <hi>minds</hi> againſt the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canonical</hi> Actions of his enemies, and to tell them that ſuch proceedings were not <hi>bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and that they would be pleaſed, till his cauſe was duely tryed, to let him continue in their good <hi>eſteem,</hi> and to look upon him as a <hi>Brother,</hi> and vouchſafe him their <hi>love</hi> and <hi>communion;</hi> would this argue, that our Arch-biſhop and his Suffragons, are the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream <hi>Heads</hi> of the <hi>Catholick Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. By all this you may ſee, that thoſe <hi>Applications</hi> which were upon occaſion made to the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> by foreign
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:50211:32"/>
Bishops, are no good argument to prove that his unlimitted power over all Churches, which is now contended for. Let us now conſider the laſt point, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any ſuch thing can be concluded from thoſe <hi>Acts,</hi> which did ſometimes <hi>follow</hi> after ſuch Applications. For the Author of <hi>Nubes Teſtium</hi> doth <hi>Appropriate</hi> divers acts to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> for which his Collections cannot bear him out. As, 1. The ſole power of <hi>depoſing</hi> other Prelates, that which was ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the proper buſineſs of <hi>Synods,</hi> as <hi>Petrus de Marca</hi> abundantly ſhews, and which he confeſſes was not obtained by the Pope till <hi>about Eight hundred years ago.</hi> As for <hi>Neſtorius</hi> (whom this Author doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Concord. l.</hi> 7. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1 § 7.</note> in) he was Depoſed by the <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſine</hi> Council; nor was the Pope con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in it more than any other Biſhop. Becauſe he was ſuch a notorious and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate Heretick, all the Biſhops of the Catholick Church were engaged in a <hi>common cauſe</hi> againſt him. St. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> would have Excommunicated him <hi>before,</hi> as he ſignified in his Epiſtle to Pope <hi>Caeleſtine,</hi> who in his Anſwer to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:50211:33"/>
               <hi>Cyril concurr'd</hi> with him, and <hi>conſented</hi> to it, as any other Biſhop might have done. He did not <hi>delegate</hi> any power which St. <hi>Cyril</hi> had not of himſelf, ſo making him his <hi>Subſtitute</hi> (as this Author is pleaſe to Romance) but onely went hand in hand with him, <hi>joining</hi> the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the</hi> Roman <hi>See with his.</hi> And <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Ep.</hi> Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtine <hi>ad Cyril.</hi>
               </note> when the <hi>Epheſine</hi> Council depoſed <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorius,</hi> it was the Authority of the <hi>Church-Canons</hi> they went upon; and tho' they took notice of Pope <hi>Caeleſtine</hi>'s <hi>Letter</hi> to them, it was only in <hi>commendation</hi> of him, that they might <hi>extol him for his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs in that matter,</hi> as they ſaid in their Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodical Epiſtle to the Emperors <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Valentinian.</hi> Nay, tho' <hi>Caeleſtine</hi> had cenſur'd <hi>Neſtorius</hi> before that Council met, yet he did it in a <hi>Synod</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> with the <hi>conſent</hi> and <hi>joint-concurrence</hi> of a great many Bishops more; ſo that in all that affair the Pope uſed no more Authority, than other Bishops did.</p>
            <p>2. Beſides this, our Author appropriates to the Pope the power of <hi>reſtoring</hi> Bishops that had been outed of their Bishop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks; and ſo he pretends that he reſtored
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:50211:33"/>
               <hi>Euſtathius, Athanaſius</hi> and the reſt. But as for <hi>Euſtathius,</hi> he was reſtored by the Synod at <hi>Tyana;</hi> and that at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, not of the Pope onely, but a great many other Bishops in <hi>Italy, France, Africk, Sicily,</hi> and <hi>Illyricum;</hi> nay, at the inſtance of the Emperor himſelf; for he went to that Synod with Letters from all theſe, as 'tis acknowledged. 'Tis true, the Weſtern Bishops <hi>concurr'd,</hi> and gave <hi>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion</hi> to the reſt to do ſo too, for which St. <hi>Baſil</hi> blames them. But if the Pope had the <hi>ſole</hi> power in his hand, why did <hi>Euſtathius</hi> go to any other? What need had he to give himſelf ſo much <hi>trouble,</hi> having once made a friend of the Pope? And as for <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and the other Eaſtern Bishops, who our Author ſaith <note place="margin">Pag. 30, 31.</note> were reſtored to their Sees, by Pope <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> it is evident by the whole ſtory, and honeſtly confeſt by <hi>Petrus de Marca,</hi> that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Concord. Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>C.</hi> 3. 7.</note> their Reſtitution was <hi>decreed</hi> by the <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dican</hi> Council, and was actually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured and effected by the Emperors <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</hi> 'Tis true, Pope <hi>Julius receiv'd</hi> thoſe Bishops into his <hi>Communion,</hi> becauſe he believ'd they were unjuſtly depos'd by
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:50211:34"/>
the <hi>Arian</hi> Faction. 'Tis true too, that he <hi>wrote</hi> into the Eaſt for the reſtitution of thoſe Bishops<hi>:</hi> but 'tis as true, that he pretended not to any <hi>power</hi> of doing this <hi>himſelf,</hi> but that thoſe great men ought not to be ejected without the knowledge and conſent of <hi>himſelf</hi> and <hi>other</hi> Bishops of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt.</hi> This <hi>Petrus de Marca</hi> proves undeniably, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid. Cap.</hi> 4.</note> quarrels with <hi>Baronius, Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Perron,</hi> for <hi>wreſting</hi> the ſenſe of <hi>Julius</hi> his Epiſtle <hi>to their own Opinion</hi> (juſt as our Author hath done) And as touching <hi>Sozo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi>'s words, which our Author quotes, that Learned Writer ſhews in the ſame place how they are <hi>abuſed;</hi> and that they are to be underſtood, not as if the reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of thoſe Bishops was effected <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly,</hi> or by vertue of <hi>Julius</hi> his ſupream <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> but by <hi>Conſequence</hi> onely; that is, <hi>Julius</hi> his Example and Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion had ſuch an Influence upon other Bishops and the Emperors, that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the <hi>means</hi> and <hi>occaſion</hi> of the Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and his injured Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. And now what is all this to prove, the <hi>ſole</hi> ſupream <hi>Authority</hi> of the Bishop
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:50211:34"/>
of <hi>Rome?</hi> Eſpecially ſince <hi>Athanaſius</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf acknowledg'd, that he was reſtored by the ſuffrage <hi>of no leſs than Three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred forty and four Biſhops.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, if you think I have been too pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix upon this Theme, I muſt intreat you to conſider that it is one of the moſt Principal of thoſe points which are in Controverſie between Us, and the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and a point of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence. I hope that by what has been Written, you will be able rightly to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand thoſe paſſages which the Author of the <hi>Nubes Teſtium</hi> hath collected upon this Head; and before I paſs on to the the next point, I ſhall take notice but of Four paſſages more.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He ſaith, the <hi>General Council of</hi> Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon <hi>own'd the ſupream Authority of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 44.</note> 
               <hi>Pope; inaſmuch as the chief accuſation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> Dioſcorus <hi>was, that contrary to the Tradition and Practice of the Church, he had preſumed to call a Council, without the conſent of the Biſhop of</hi> Rome; <hi>as appears from the words of</hi> Lucentius, <hi>Legate from the See Apoſtolick,</hi> Act. 1. But this he <hi>falſiſies</hi> wretchedly. For the Crimes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:50211:35"/>
againſt <hi>Dioſcorus,</hi> (Bishop of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria)</hi> were, that he was a <hi>Favourer</hi> of the Heretick <hi>Eutyches,</hi> and was guilty of <hi>Outrages</hi> and <hi>bloodſhed.</hi> This made the great Outcry in the Council, that he ſhould be <hi>turned out</hi> of it. Indeed <hi>Lucentius</hi> (the Popes Legate) pleaded, that <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> had called a Synod without the Popes Authority. But this allegation was not <hi>admitted,</hi> nor taken notice of by the Council; they required <hi>Lucentius</hi> to ſhew, <hi>wherein</hi> Dioſcorus <hi>had offended?</hi> And when <hi>Lucentius perſiſted</hi> in his allegation, the Fathers <hi>reprehended him for accuſing him;</hi> and ſo <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> was commanded <hi>to keep his place;</hi> which he did till he was caſt out for <hi>other</hi> reaſons. If you conſult the firſt action of the <hi>Chalcedon-Council,</hi> you will find what I ſay to be True; and by that you may judge, whether they lookt upon <hi>Lucentius</hi> his allegation to have been any <hi>Crime</hi> in <hi>Dioſcorus,</hi> as this Author would make you believe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He tells us, that the <hi>Monks of</hi> Syria, <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> Hormiſda <hi>the Pope, the Head of all.</hi> And can we believe, that thoſe men, who were then perſecuted by the <hi>Eutychians</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:50211:35"/>
neglected by the Emperor, would apply themſelves to <hi>Hormiſda</hi> without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plementing him with an Honourable <hi>Title?</hi> Yet that Title imports no more, but that he was one of the principal Bishops of the Catholick Church; and ſuch Titles were uſually given to any very Eminent Biſhope ſpecially if he was a Patriarch. For ſo St. <hi>Baſil</hi> himſelf ſaid of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch <note place="margin">Baſil. <hi>Ep.</hi> 52.</note> of <hi>Alexandria, that he had the care of all the Churches; and that he thought it moſt convenient for them to fly to him, as the Head of them all, and to make uſe of him as their Counſellor, as their Captain and Prince in the government of their affairs.</hi> What a noiſe ſhould we have about our ears, had St. <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaid ſo much of the Patriarch of <hi>Rome?</hi> And yet St. <hi>Baſil</hi> did not mean, that <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> was the <hi>ſupream <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Paſtor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. He ſaith, that <hi>the firſt Council at</hi> Conſtantinople <hi>deſir'd their Decrees to be confirm'd by Pope</hi> Damaſus; <hi>eſpecially as to the depoſing of</hi> Timotheus, <hi>an</hi> Apollinariſt. But this doth not appear<hi>:</hi> for all that the Council required of him was, that he, being abſent from the Council, would
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:50211:36"/>
               <hi>concur</hi> with them in the condemnation of the Heretick. Now this was no argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Damaſus</hi> his <hi>Supremacy:</hi> For <hi>all</hi> Bishops were <hi>bound</hi> to do the <hi>ſame</hi> thing: <hi>all</hi> of them were ingaged againſt an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, as in a <hi>common Cauſe,</hi> and as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a <hi>common Enemy.</hi> Thus <hi>Novatian</hi> was excommunicated by ſeveral Synods in <hi>Rome, Italy,</hi> and <hi>Africa;</hi> nay, by all the Bishops over the World, as <hi>Petrus de Marca</hi> doth confeſs out of St. <hi>Cyprian.</hi> And the reaſon given is this, becauſe <hi>all the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Concord. Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>C.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Biſhops were but one body; an Order of men that were <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited together; ſo that if an Heretical Biſhop aroſe in any Province, all the Biſhops were preſently to lend their help and aſſiſtance againſt him.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it is notorious, that by the Canons of the Catholick Church, <hi>no Biſhop was to receive any man into his Communion that had been juſtly Excommunicated by another.</hi> So that when the Council of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople requir'd Damaſus</hi> (for that is the word) to <hi>concur</hi> with them againſt <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus,</hi> they onely <hi>requir'd</hi> him to obſerve the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of the whole Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church. It was no token of his <hi>Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:50211:36"/>
over them, but of his fraternal <hi>Communion</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> with them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſt of all, our Author produces the definition of the <hi>Florentine</hi> Council, that <hi>the Holy Apoſtolick See, and Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>has the Primacy over the whole World,</hi> &amp;c. But ſurely a man that entitles his book, <hi>A Collection of the Primitive Fathers,</hi> ſhould have left out this Council, which was not Three hundred years ago, far from a Council of <hi>Primitive</hi> men. And as for thoſe <hi>Fathers</hi> (if they muſt be called ſo) every one knows, that there were not Thirty <hi>Greek</hi> Biſhops among them; nor were the <hi>Latines</hi> any other, than ſuch as were packt and ſhuffled together, to play the Popes Game for him. Nor was the Popes Primacy <hi>debated</hi> at all among the <hi>Legates:</hi> No, the great buſineſs was about the manner of the <hi>Proceſſion</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt<hi>:</hi> And when ſome of the <hi>Greeks</hi> were perſwaded at laſt to ſubſcribe to <hi>that</hi> Article, the poor <hi>Greek</hi> Emperor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wearied out by <hi>delayes,</hi> ſubſcribed the Doctrines of <hi>Purgatory, of the Popes Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>himſelf,</hi> not ſo much as <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting</hi> the matter to the <hi>Greek Legates.</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:50211:37"/>
This was the fine Council of <hi>Fathers,</hi> whoſe definition our Author reckons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt; though perhaps with a deſign to make up that by <hi>Tale,</hi> which was wanting in <hi>Weight.</hi> I ſay no more of that Council, becauſe you may ſee enough to invalidate the Authority of it, by that account which our Learned Dr. <hi>Stilling-fleet</hi> has given, out of <hi>Sguropulus,</hi> in his defence of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church. But having ſaid thus much concerning this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, I ſhall the next time endeavour to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie you in that point concerning <hi>Images and Image-worſhip,</hi> about which the <hi>next</hi> great <hi>Controverſie</hi> was in the Ancient Church.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:50211:37"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
